A Search for Solid Ground: The Intifada Through Israeli Eyes
is a documentary film directed by Steve Brand.
Hodding Carter hosts the program, which includes another look at the Gaza
Strip-West Bank uprising and a panel discussion on recent peace proposals.
Self - Host, played by Hodding Carter III.
Since its foundation in 1948, Israel has been accused of carrying out genocide
against Palestinians during the Israeli–Palestinian conflict.
A wide consensus of scholars have concluded that Israel's actions during the Gaza war since 2023 constitute genocide, although debate continues over whether Israel's
treatment of Palestinians since the Nakba—prior to 2023—also constitutes genocide, and whether such actions are continuous or limited to specific periods or events.
This treatment has also been characterised as "slow-motion genocide", as well as a
corollary or expression of settler colonialism and indigenous land theft.
Those who believe Israel's actions constitute genocide point to the entrenched anti-Palestinianism, anti-Arab racism, Islamophobia and genocidal rhetoric in Israeli society, and point to events
such as the Nakba, the Sabra and Shatila massacre, the blockade of the Gaza Strip, the 2014 Gaza War, and the 2023–present Gaza war as particularly pertinent genocidal episodes.
International law and genocide scholars have accused Israeli
officials of using dehumanising language.
Following the outbreak of the Gaza war in 2023 after the October 7 attacks, Israeli Holocaust historian Omer Bartov warned that
statements made by high-ranking Israeli government officials "could easily be construed as indicating a genocidal intent".
On 29 December 2023, South Africa filed a case against Israel at the International Court of
Justice, alleging that Israel's conduct in Gaza during the 2023 war amounted to genocide.
South Africa asked the ICJ to issue provisional measures, including
ordering Israel to halt its military campaign in Gaza.
The Israeli government agreed to defend itself at the ICJ proceedings, while also denouncing South
Africa's actions as "disgraceful" and accusing it of abetting "the modern heirs of the Nazis".
South Africa's case has been supported by a number of countries.
On 26 January 2024, the ICJ issued a preliminary ruling finding that the claims in South Africa's filing were "plausible" and issued an order to Israel
requiring them to take all measures within their power to prevent acts of genocide and to allow basic humanitarian services into Gaza.
In March 2024, the UN special rapporteur on the situation of human rights in the occupied Palestinian territories, Francesca Albanese, issued a report
stating that there were "reasonable grounds to believe that the threshold indicating the commission" of acts of genocide had been met.
Israel rejected the report.
Israel and the United States have rejected the assertion
that the former is engaging in genocide.
While some scholars describe Palestinians as victims of genocide, others argue that what took
place was ethnic cleansing, politicide, spaciocide, cultural genocide or similar.
Some critics of the accusation have argued that charges of Israel committing genocide are
commonly made by anti-Zionists with the aim of delegitimising or demonising Israel.